I'm thankful that most academics are
such terrible writers great he gives you
a job I'm Angela Duckworth I'm Steven
Dubner and you're list listening to no
stupid
questions today on the show how do you
get people to work for free without
their even knowing it it's like better
than Tom Sawyer really he just painted a
freaking fence yeah also there are
millions of academic articles published
each year but how much is this research
actually benefiting us not even other
scientists are are reading these
articles and not even scientists mothers
very likely
[Applause]
not Angela Stephen nice to see you it is
great to see you special occasion today
very special I think our first ever
guest on no stupid questions and I think
he may be a remarkable guest I think
he's absolutely a remarkable guest but
we should probably lower the
expectations I think he'll be an okay
guess he's fine great guys great so Luis
vanan is probably best known for for
being the creator of du lingo the
popular app for learning foreign
languages hi Luis welcome could you give
us a kind of 60-second version of your
entire
life I am currently the CEO of a company
called dual lingo we teach languages was
born and grew up in Guatemala came to
the US for college I was a professor of
computer science at Carnegie Millan
University and something else that I did
that became pretty popular is these
distorted characters that you have to
type all over the intern to prove that
you're a human it's called a capture and
it stands for something clever it's an
acronym yes it's completely automated
public turning test to tell computers
and humans of art it's a mouthful and
this was to get the other end of a
computer to prove that you were a human
and not another computer that's correct
for example to prevent people from
buying all of the tickets for a concert
on Ticket Master that didn't work very
well cuz they still do they do but it
prevents other things for example it
prevents things like people from writing
programs to obtain million of free email
accounts Luis vanan I have a question
for you now and it goes like this what
do Luis vanan and Tom Sawyer have in
common I'm going to guess it probably
has to do with tricking somebody to
paint a fence I was not going to use the
word trick a positive version of I was
going to use the word entice so you
remember the Tom Sawyer story you know I
actually don't remember it super well
angre do you remember the Tom don't okay
so in Adventures of Tom Sawyer Tom
Sawyer's Aunt Polly tells him his
Saturday chore is to White Wash or paint
this really tall fence and he's bummed
because you know he'd rather be fishing
or swimming or playing and then he
decides well what if I persuade people
that this is not grunt work but a novel
and awesome thing to do and then his
friends start coming by and pretty soon
not only have they painted the fence in
turns but he's made them pay him for the
privilege of painting in the fence so
here's a short passage when the middle
of the afternoon came from being a poor
poverty stricken boy in the morning Tom
was literally rolling in wealth and so
in the least pejorative way possible I
thought of you when I was reading about
the way you've built your companies
which is incredibly ingenious and it
seems like it helps everybody but can
you explain what I mean by you being Tom
Sawyer in that regard yeah for a while a
lot of my research had a lot to do with
how do you entice people to do things
that computerss cannot do when I was a
first year graduate student I helped
invent these captas and can you tell the
story of how you even knew that that was
a function that computers needed I was
at Carnegie Mill University and the guy
who at the time was the chief scientist
of Yahoo his name was Udi mber came to
give a talk and the talk was about 10
problems that they didn't know how to
solve at Yahoo and Yahoo we should say
was a big deal at the time was the
single biggest internet company Yahoo
was like Google is today was huge and
then they had these 10 problems I Now
understand that the reason he came to
give the stock was to recruit potential
employees I thought he actually needed
help solving these problems but one of
the problems he talked about was they
didn't know how to stop people from
writing programs to obtain millions of
email accounts for free the people who
wanted to do that were spammers each
account only allowed you to send like
500 messages a day but if you wanted to
send 50 million emails you needed
millions of accounts from which to send
the spam messages so they wanted a way
to stop this and people were just
writing Bots to sign up for millions of
email accounts that's right and so first
we came up with a more general idea like
what if we could come up with a test
that can distinguish whether the thing
that is getting an email account is
actually a human or a computer see a
human's not going to get 50 million
email accounts cuz they'll lose patience
but a computer would get 50 million so
if we could distinguish between humans
and computers then we could solve the
problem and by the way this is an old
IDE in computer science distinguishing
between a human computer is called a
Turing test this was proposed by Alan
Turing many people call him the father
of computing his idea was a computer
will be intelligent once somebody cannot
really determine whether they're talking
to a human or to a computer now in this
case was a human judge trying to tell
whether they're talking to a computer or
a human in the case for this problem
that we were trying to solve we need a
computer to be able to determine whether
it was talking to a human or a computer
we needed a test that a computer could
administer and grade but not pass at
first this seems paradox but then when
you're your professor you actually
realize this is not that uncommon you
can administer tests without being able
to pass them I definitely did that so so
anyways the idea was that the more
general idea and then at some point we
came up with a specific one which was at
the time computers were not very good at
reading images of distorted text but
humans were so this is something that a
computer can actually administer and
grade so a computer starts by putting
some letters on an image then it
distorts them all you have to do is just
match the the sort of letter so that was
the idea with a capture were there other
ideas you had that didn't work there
were others that did work but just not
as well for example we could give you a
bunch of pictures of like flowers and
then just ask you what are these
pictures of and then you would have to
type the word flower is that too
open-ended yeah it was too open-ended it
was harder it required people to know
how to spell I was going to say there's
a little bit of human skill here not
everybody knows how to spell whereas the
beautiful thing about the distorted
letters is that for every letter there's
actually a key on the keyboard and
humans happen to be pretty good at that
and it worked beautifully it worked
beautifully I mean pretty quickly
essentially every website out there was
using it in one way or another to stop
people from writing programs that would
abuse the system at the time about 200
million times a day somebody would type
a capture on the internet so could we
somehow figure out how to get them to do
something useful and this is where it
occurred to me that you could get them
to help us digitize books Google was
trying to digitize all of the world's
books and the way that works is you take
a book and you take a digital photograph
of every page of the book that gives you
images with words in them
the next step is that the computer needs
to decipher all of these words but for
older books the computer could not
decipher all the words or even probably
some fonts yeah it was harder or the
picture was not super clear or something
the computer could not recognize about
30% of the words the way we hooked up
the whole process was we took the
pictures from the book and then the
words that the computer could not
understand we would send them to people
while they were typing captas on the
internet so Google ended up buying your
company correct yes but even before that
you were licensed ing your technology to
the New York Times for instance to
digitize its archives yeah so the captas
were not just random words the captas
were not just random words they were
actually coming from books that the
computer could not recognize and we
would use what people were typing to
help digitize this stuff and you didn't
know that I didn't know that so as you
learn that think back you've probably
filled in a few thousand captas in your
life I feel like I didn't get paid for
any of that that's what I was going to
ask do you feel like I didn't get paid
or do you feel like oh my gosh that's so
awesome that in the process of me doing
this thing that I needed to do to get
what I wanted to get I also helped
digitize an archiv I think it's great I
wonder did anybody ever know a lot of
people knew and we actually didn't try
to hide it there was a big question mark
in there that when you clicked on it it
would tell you what it was it turned out
most people didn't click on it so there
was like a little button that said
you're helping digitize things so we
were getting these words and we were
sending them to people while they were
getting a Facebook account or whatever
they were helping us to digitize the New
York Times can I just say I think that's
awesome that is Gen I mean I just think
it's so clever that you were able to
repurpose labor it's like better than
Tom Sawyer really it is better than Tom
he just painted a freaking fence and
it's going to need to be painted again
like in 3 years and once the New York
Times is digitized it won't is it still
true though haven't computers gotten
better at being able to read distorted
text so computers have gotten way better
what has happened over time is that the
modern versions of captas the secure
ones are unlikely to use distored
characters now and they're back to this
original idea of pictures of things like
you get pictures of street signs and
you're ask which of these is not a stop
sign why can't they do that I mean gosh
that sounds like a great task for a
computer I I think in most cases they
can this comes because something like
Google Maps is trying to map all of the
world and they're trying to recognize
all of the stop signs in the world
whenever the computer is not very sure
that it saw a stop sign it says oh okay
here's what I'm going to do I'm going to
send it to somebody that's trying to get
an email account somewhere and I'm going
to ask them is this a stop sign or not
and so you're helping basically build
much better Maps or build better image
recognition or something like that so is
there any of this win-win logic at the
heart of du lingo there was at the
beginning there no longer is oh I was
hoping there still was so just explain
what Duolingo is and how it works so
primarily it is an app to learn
languages it's now the most popular way
to learn languages in the world there
are more people learning languages on
Dual lingual in the United States than
there are people learning languages in
the whole US public school system we
have 10 times as many people learning
Irish on Dual lingo than they are Irish
native speakers and you have a lot of
people learning Game of Thrones and Star
Trek languages are you kidding make of
it what you will there are more people
learning High Valyrian on Dual lingo
from Game of Thrones than there are
people learning
Irish can we also just quickly do the
business proposition you're still
privately held correct it is a private
company Venture funded Venture funded
company and the last I read the
valuation was in the neighborhood of1
and a.2 billion dollar yeah about one
and a half billion most of your product
the vast majority is free correct so how
are you worth one and a half billion
yeah so you can learn a language
entirely for free on du lingo in fact
this was the mission of the company in
part because learning English can really
change your life you know it's nice to
learn French to go and order you know a
croissant in Paris but really learning
English in non-english speaking
countries can double your income
potential there is data that shows that
learning a second language if you're an
English-speaking American is pretty much
useless I think it's the lowest rated
skill fromy ERS in a recent survey but
if it were high valarian maybe yeah I
wasn't on the survey well but there's
other things by the way I of course have
to be here to tell you about all the
benefits of learning a language it is
also good for your brain good for
executive function prefrontal cor yeah
but the mission has really been always
to be able to teach for free is that
related to your coming from Guatemala
where English is an incredibly valuable
skill yes it's entirely not only is it
an incredibly valuable skill it's a very
poor country and everybody wanted to
learn English and nobody had money and
the all the ways the word to learn
English were really expensive so if I'm
writing the Louis fonan biography like
the hagiography I say listen if you
Angela are feeling a little bit
exploited that you didn't get paid for
entering all those captas you should
know that he plowed the money back into
a way to teach everyone English around
the world for free I'm good with them I
feel like we're even now so the way we
make money is we had to be consistent
with our mission so the first thing that
occurred to us is just put an ad at the
end of a lesson it turns out we have
enough users that that actually made us
you know T of millions of dollars a year
soon after that we added a subscription
where the main thing the subscription
did was turn off the ads we make way
more money from the subscription than
from the ads what percentage of your
users turn off the ads so 3% of our
users are paying subscribers but even
being only 3% outweighs the revenue from
the ANS significantly 85% of our Revenue
comes from those 3% of the users that's
the way Spotify works as well there are
a lot more free users but the premium
well more than make up for it it's
exactly the same thing so last year we
made $90 million from this and then this
year we're probably going to double it
we're thinking about going public so I'm
not supposed to give too many estimates
it's just us in the room there's no
microphones or anything um so you said
that in the beginning du lingo used the
translation for a different purpose can
you describe that yeah in the beginning
it was a very similar idea to this book
digitization what can we get out of
people learning a language can we get
something useful from them computers
cannot yet do and at the time the idea
was could we get them to translate stuff
for free for us so what we did is we
actually had contracts with CNN and
buzfeed they would write all their news
in English they would give it to us and
then we would have these users that were
learning English on Dual lingo and then
after a certain point we would say hey
you want to practice what you just
learned here's a CNN article in English
why don't you help us translate it to
your native language imagine they were
Native Spanish speakers so they would to
practice their English would help us
translate the article to Spanish and
then we would get multiple users to
translate the same kind of paragraphs
and stuff and then a computer program
would kind of combine all of it and then
we would give a translation back to CNN
who would pay us for this translation it
had one huge problem though translation
is a crappy business to be in because
the prices are always going down and
computer translation is getting better
and better can I say you're the first
computer scientist I've ever spoken with
who afterward I understood a little bit
better about how to think about problem
solving and it didn't just make me feel
confused oh thank you there are other
computers
I'm sure there's a few but uh but I've
also had some wildly baffling convers
where I really try to understand because
you know Computing is a Marvel
especially for those who don't really
understand it very well it seems like
magic and I want it to not be magic I've
often asked to understand different
pieces of it and I kind of gain a little
bit of an understanding but the way you
approach it it's not about the bits and
the bites it's about humanity and how to
kind of manipulate the relationship in
the right way so I appreciate your
explaining things so well well thank you
still to come on no stupid questions Lis
fonan answers Angela's question about
the volume of academic research being
produced these days we could do
something like if you publish too many
papers that have very few citations you
get tenure taken away oh I like that
relegation relegation from the academy
so you just got to watch out you just
can't publish dumb papers
[Music]
welcome back to no stupid questions
today Angela and Steven are speaking
with Luis fonan the computer scientist
who invented Capa and is now the CEO of
the language app du lingo I am really
interested in Louis's position on
scientific productivity I do believe we
should be producing scientific insights
into everything but I I realized that
there are something like one or even two
million depending on the estimate that
you read new scientific articles
produced every year and the typical
article will get you know any 01 maybe
two citations meaning not even other
scientists are in any obvious way
reading these articles so and not even
scientists mothers maybe not most likely
not very likely not so Lou says somebody
who began as a professor in computer
science or at least was at one point in
your career and then moved outside of
Academia into the quote unquote Real
World what do you think about whether
there is utility in these many many many
articles that are being produced well
that's not an easy question but what I I
never really like this about being a
professor is I think a lot of people
including me I was guilty of this they
think the end goal is the paper not the
result and some of the people that I
admire the most did not have that many
papers throughout their career each one
of them really changed the world I think
that we should strive to be a lot more
like that in computer science in
particular you know you hear of people
who have 14 papers at the same
conference I can tell you this I kind of
don't care how smart you are you cannot
have 14 world changing Amazing Ideas in
one year you just can't but to some
degree you can't blame the perpetrators
so much themselves because the incentive
structure is set up to encourage that
right 100% the problem is you need a way
to measure it the measurement kind of
got in the way right so measurement was
always number of citations number of
papers these are supposed to be proxies
for the impact of your scientific
discoveries but now I feel like we're
chasing the metric and then that has led
to kind of this like citation arms race
20 or 30 years ago to become a tenear
professor there was an expectation of
some small number of citations and
papers and now it's just exploded where
you can't even get interviewed for a job
unless you have a reasonably long vaita
with lots of Articles it's crazy and
also things like Google Scholar really
helped to do this because now you can
count very easily how many citations
somebody has and then your worth as a
scientist is you have 2,000 citations or
10,000 citations or 30,000 citations you
mentioned people who are great in their
field which I I guess you mean your
field computer science right yeah who've
published only maybe a handful of papers
can you give an example a good example
was my PhD adviser Manuel Blum very
prominent in the field I mean he got the
Turing award which is kind of the Nobel
Prize for computer science he's a
cryptographer he helped invent modern
cryptography has more than a handful of
papers but he really didn't seem to
publish more than a couple of papers per
year and there's a few of them that are
really really the beginnings of some
amazing things what motivated him and if
he wasn't motivated by citation count
how would you characterize what woke him
up in the morning kept him working so
hard I think in his case he truly truly
wanted to understand things when I
started working with him I would try to
explain something to him and he he would
say I'm sorry I don't understand and he
did that many many times at some point I
started kind of wondering well this guy
smart I seem to be saying very simple
stuff but he just wants to have a really
deep understanding of things and at some
point I started realizing what a deep
understanding meant for example if you
have a really deep understanding of
something you can explain it really well
these people who can't explain things
super well they probably don't have that
great of an understanding of things so
did you learn at that point that you
didn't really fully understand even your
own idea correct and he helped you do
that without telling you that's what he
was doing exactly and I got much better
at explaining certain things I mean it'd
be like the first line and he'd say I'm
sorry I I don't understand and you know
it really kind of pissed me off he still
doesn't understand one thing and he's
still at it um he wants to understand
Consciousness this is the thing he has
wanted to understand his entire life
what does that mean to understand
Consciousness I'm not even sure maybe
you should turn the table say I'm sorry
Manuel I don't understand what you mean
by this idea can you explain it to me
it's a pretty complex thing right I mean
Consciousness I mean I'm sure you guys
know way more about this particularly
Angela being an academic in this field I
mean there's something about this the
thing that's controlling us right you
know if you're sitting in the park you
think you have Consciousness and you see
a squirrel chasing an acor and you
presume that the squirrel does not have
the kind of Consciousness we have and
then you go into a tail spin of like but
how would I know do computer scientists
actually think about questions like this
yes yes yes particularly early
artificial intelligence researchers
really wondered what will it take for a
computer to be able to do everything
that a human can and then you start
wondering well okay do they need to be
conscious you know from the outside of
all they're doing is the same input
output Behavior who cares whether
they're conscious or not so you say
early AI or maybe even early computer
people it reminds me a little bit of
like the earliest economists going back
a few hundred years ago they were moral
philosophers and economics was just kind
of like the nitty-gritty way of
measuring how people were changing as
society and industry was changing do you
see a similar kind of generational shift
among computer scientists that there was
more whether it's philosophy or that
kind of higher order thinking than now
cuz I think a lot of people now when
they hear about someone going to school
now for computer science they almost
think of it as like a very very very
high-end trade school because there's an
industry it's a great vocation and so
I'm curious whether the field has
continued to produce and encourage that
kind of philosophical thinking I think
it has definitely shifted from the early
days I think these people were a lot
more philosophical and they really were
trying to answer very fundamental
questions about what it means to be a
human I mean now you go to school for
computer science and you can get a very
high paying job at Google or at Facebook
so it's a different type of person has
started going into the field that
doesn't mean that there's nobody out
there thinking about all the Deep
questions but overwhelmingly I would say
it's become a lot more pragmatic okay so
getting back to Angela's original
question about all these papers as a lay
person I would think wow 2 million new
papers every year that's fantastic we're
broadening scientific knowledge so much
but if the preponderance of it is some
form of job audition SL academic status
climbing SL virtue signaling SL whatever
then it's not so good right it's very
hard to say whether this is good or not
I mean there's the other argument which
is like if you're trying to be creative
and 99% of the stuff you come up with is
going to be crap there's some research
that says look you just need volume of
ideas there is this theory of creativity
from Dean Keith simonon it's called the
equal odds Rule and it says exactly that
you want a good idea we'll start with 10
ideas maybe one of them will be good
okay you want two good ideas generate 20
ideas I mean it's really just a linear
function and more is better how should a
non academic researcher feel about all
the research produced by academics the
vast majority of which is written for a
tiny cohort of your peers in a language
that is literally indecipherable to the
lay person maybe not psychology papers
but comps and a lot of Economics should
we feel it as a kind of this is going to
sound too fresh like some Elite
masturbatory Festival where you guys are
all in your lovely Ivory Towers doing
doing research that very rarely trickles
down or affects us and yet is often
funded by some version of taxpayer you
know I'm not saying that academic
researchers should focus on news you can
use kind of research but it does seem
extraordinarily corded off including the
fact that academic journals will cost
$20,000 a year very few people will
actually access them so how do you just
feel about that from the production end
that's an excellent question I think
there are some academics who role a lot
of times is to translate research and I
think they get very good at it Angela
being one of these people not your
entire role but you've done a really
good job just translating a lot of
research I try I'm thankful that most
academics are such terrible writers
great it gives you a job yeah I would be
useless I think there should be more
people that try to translate things to
the general audience should universities
spend more time doing that themselves or
should the journals I mean some journals
actually to their credit now do like NBR
the National Bureau of economic research
they send out all the working papers
every week which is usually 25 or 30
papers and then once a week they do a
digest that's kind of written in you
know journalism form and those are the
papers that get written about in The New
York Times and Wall Street Journal much
more often because you know reporters
might be right people but they may not
read all 30 economic papers every week
and so I figure that's a good function
but I still feel just that there's a
kind of loss to society that there's all
this brain power and good ideas because
every time I meet an academic it can
meet in a very obscure field and I
always ask them you know what do you
think about what are you working on they
always have something amazing always and
I'm like I've never heard a thing about
that where would I have read that and
it's like well in the Journal of
left-handed cardiological you know okay
so here's a theory as probably Manuel
will tell you it's not easy to write
clearly even for your peers also if
you're not a very clear thinker or an
especially good writer there's a kind of
retreat into the Dazzle them yeah with
syllables with formulas with formulas
and passive tense sentences that are
really long I have mixed feelings on the
one hand more scientific discovery is
better but it's absolutely true there's
this strange incentive system at work
where you are personally awarded on
volume and it would be better if we had
an incentive system that rewarded
quality and not quantity right now I
think it's rewarding both but the
metrics are so much more visible when it
comes to Quant than quality I don't have
any brilliant ideas of how to make the
system better we could do something like
if you publish too many papers that have
very few citations you get tenure taken
away oh I like that relegation
relegation from the academy so you just
got to watch out you just can't publish
dumb papers okay I want you to start
that movement and I'm going to sign on
to be your enforcer that would be so
much fun we will not be loved by the
academic world it's okay it's not my
world
no stupid questions is part of the fre
economics radio network this episode was
produced by me Rebecca Lee Douglas and
now here's a fact check of today's
questions in the first half of the
episode Luis explains that the original
purpose of Capa was to help prevent Bots
from signing up for spam accounts he
says that each account only allows you
to send 500 emails per day which is true
that's the sending limit for both Yahoo
and Gmail however he goes on to s that
if a spammer wants to send 50 million
emails they would need to register for
millions of accounts Luis may be a
computer science genius but he might
need to brush up on his basic arithmetic
if Yahoo allows you to send 500 emails
per day you only need 100,000 accounts
to send 50 million outbound messages
that is within a period of 24 hours this
would still be quite challenging for a
single person say it takes a human 1
minute to register for a new Yahoo email
even if you did nothing but register for
accounts all day and you didn't eat or
sleep or use the bathroom it would still
take approximately 69 days 10 hours and
40 minutes to register 100,000 accounts
so you need to have some extreme
Devotion to fake Nigerian princes or to
scientifically unproven mail enhancement
drugs in the second half of the episode
Angela says that there are between 1 and
2 million scientific AR articles
published each year but according to the
International Association of scientific
Technical and medical Publishers the
number is actually more like 3 million
Louis was concerned that some academics
publish 14 articles a year but authors
have been known to publish more than 72
papers a year an equivalent to one paper
every 5 days Steph laments how
challenging it can be for Lay people to
access academic journals which he says
can cost $20,000 a year depending on the
quality of the journals and the level of
access this number can actually be much
higher a subscription to ele the world's
biggest publisher of academic research
can cost universities a whopping $10
million a year however in recent years
there's been a push for open access to
Scientific journals government agencies
like the National Institutes of Health
and the National Science Foundation now
require grantees to make their work Open
Access a year after public
scientists are also increasingly
publishing pre-publication versions of
their work online so that anyone can
view it without a payall unfortunately
that means that the studies haven't yet
been peer-reviewed but many believe that
this is a step in the direction of open
access to scientific information for all
that's it for the fact
check no stupid questions is produced by
Freakonomics radio and Stitcher our
staff includes Allison krao Greg rippen
James Foster and Wallace our theme song
is and she was by Talking Heads special
thanks to David burn and Warner Chapel
Music if you'd like to listen to our
show ad free subscribe to Stitcher
premium you can also follow us on
Instagram and Twitter at nsq show and on
Facebook at nsq show and if you heard
Steven or Angela refer to something that
you'd like to know more about we put
together a page of relevant links and
resources for each episode just go to
freecomic nsq thanks for
listening okay um so let's just begin
with um a greeting that feels not too
manufactured or unenthusiastic hi
Stephen yeah that very
manufactured salutations no also
bad Stitcher